<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on Ángela Castillo-Gill</title>
    <link>/post/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on Ángela Castillo-Gill</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2018 Ángela Castillo-Gill</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 09 Aug 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Predicting property prices</title>
      <link>/post/predicting-property-prices/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Aug 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/predicting-property-prices/</guid>
      <description>1 Summary 2 Purpose of this post 3 The data 4 Data exploration 5 Techniques used   1 Summary To see the code used in this post, visit my kernel on kaggle in R Markdown format.
 2 Purpose of this post  3 The data The dataset House Prices: Advanced Regression Techniques was downloaded from Kaggle and put together by Dean De Cock. It has 79 explanatory variables describing 1,460 homes in Ames, Iowa.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Exploring Kiva loans</title>
      <link>/post/exploring-kiva-loans/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 07 Jul 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/exploring-kiva-loans/</guid>
      <description>1 Summary 2 Purpose of this post 3 The data 4 Data cleaning 5 Exploratory data analysis 6 Techniques used 7 Questions from this analysis   1 Summary To see the code used in this post, visit my kernel on kaggle in R Markdown format.
In this post, I analyse 671,205 observations. Each represents a Kiva loan. I find that the gender that requests the most loans is female with single females being the most frequent borrowers.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bayesian Regression vs. Frequentist Regression</title>
      <link>/post/bayesian-regression-vs-frequentist-regression/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 May 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/bayesian-regression-vs-frequentist-regression/</guid>
      <description>So I thought, I need to get to the bottom of this, what is indeed the difference between Frequentist and Bayesian regression beyond the distinction of what probability, as a whole, means to both sides.
Ordinary Least Squared (OLS) Errors Regression With OLS, our best estimate of the line that describes the relationship between the explanatory and response variable is ordinary least squared (OLS) estimates of alpha and beta to obtain the “fitted” values of predictions.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>