<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on Ángela D. Castillo-Gill</title>
    <link>/post/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on Ángela D. Castillo-Gill</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2018 Ángela D. Castillo-Gill</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 24 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Rossman stores sales</title>
      <link>/post/rossman-stores-sales/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/rossman-stores-sales/</guid>
      <description>1 Summary 2 Purpose of this post 3 The data 4 Data cleaning 5 Exploratory data analysis 6 Techniques used 7 Questions from this analysis   1 Summary  2 Purpose of this post  3 The data The data was obtained from the Kaggle platform. After sales data with unique store data, the final data set is 986,159 observations with 18 variables. Each observation correponds to the turnover for a given day.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Exploring Kiva loans</title>
      <link>/post/clustering-kiva-loans/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Aug 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/clustering-kiva-loans/</guid>
      <description>1 Summary 2 Purpose of this post 3 The data 4 Data cleaning 5 Clustering 6 Techniques used 7 Questions from this analysis   1 Summary  2 Purpose of this post While looking at the distributions for variables like loan amounts loan_usd or loan term term_in_months, I realised that there are many types of loans represented in that plot. Therefore, I thought it would be interesting to cluster the data.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Exploring Kiva loans</title>
      <link>/post/exploring-kiva-loans/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 07 Jul 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/exploring-kiva-loans/</guid>
      <description>1 Summary 2 Purpose of this post 3 The data 4 Data cleaning 5 Exploratory data analysis 6 Techniques used 7 Questions from this analysis   1 Summary To see the code used in this post, visit my kernel on kaggle in R Markdown format.
In this post, I analyse 671,205 observations. Each represents a Kiva loan. I find that the gender that requests the most loans is female with single females being the most responsible.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bayesian Regression vs. Frequentist Regression</title>
      <link>/post/bayesian-regression-vs-frequentist-regression/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 May 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/bayesian-regression-vs-frequentist-regression/</guid>
      <description>So I thought, I need to get to the bottom of this, what is indeed the difference between Frequentist and Bayesian regression beyond the distinction of what probability, as a whole, means to both sides.
Ordinary Least Squared (OLS) Errors Regression With OLS, our best estimate of the line that describes the relationship between the explanatory and response variable is ordinary least squared (OLS) estimates of alpha and beta to obtain the “fitted” values of predictions.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>