<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>R Markdown on Ángela Castillo-Gill</title>
    <link>/tags/r-markdown/</link>
    <description>Recent content in R Markdown on Ángela Castillo-Gill</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 20 Oct 2017 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/r-markdown/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Updating your version of Hugo for blogdown on Netlify</title>
      <link>/2017/10/updating-blogdown-hugo-version-netlify/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Oct 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/10/updating-blogdown-hugo-version-netlify/</guid>
      <description>Fair warning ⚠️ All of the information that follows is indeed in blogdown: Creating Websites with R Markdown by Yihui Xie, Amber Thomas, and Alison Presmanes Hill. But, since this is the second time I got a bit lost in this process, I’m writing it up for my own (and anyone else’s incidental) edification.1
Plus, just look at all the failed deploys that happen when I mess it up…it renders my Netlify deploy panel hideous!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Keeping up with blogdown 🌟</title>
      <link>/2017/10/keeping-up-with-blogdown/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 07 Oct 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/10/keeping-up-with-blogdown/</guid>
      <description>Updated: 2018-08-30
I’ve loved blogdown 📦 for so long, that I was kind of shocked 😱 when I saw Yinui Xie’s post, Announcing blogdown: Create Websites with R Markdown, on the RStudio blog just last month!
Have people really been living without the magic ✨ of blogdown in their lives for so long?! If you are one of these people, then hopefully this post (which, yes, is really just a roundup of tweets) will inspire you to join in on the fun 👯.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Custom snippets in RStudio: ⚡ faster tweet chunks for all</title>
      <link>/2017/09/custom-snippets-in-rstudio-faster-tweet-chunks-for-all/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 30 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/09/custom-snippets-in-rstudio-faster-tweet-chunks-for-all/</guid>
      <description>✂️ Snippets in RStudio As Sean Lopp describes in his super helpful post, RStudio IDE Easy Tricks You Might’ve Missed ⭐:
 Code snippets are a shortcut to insert common boilerplate code.
 You might also refer to them as “text macros”1— either way, they’re useful for speeding up the process of doing a thing in RStudio that you do frequently. In my case, this includes inserting “tweet chunks” in blogdown posts using a Hugo shortcode.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>